<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Categories on Ryan's ML Gym</title><link>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/</link><description>Recent content in Categories on Ryan's ML Gym</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>JAX</title><link>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/jax/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/jax/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Machine Learning</title><link>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/machine-learning/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/machine-learning/</guid><description>&lt;p>Reinforcement Learning (RL) is a subfield of machine learning concerned with training agents to take actions in an environment to maximize some notion of reward. It is a computational framework for learning decision-making processes based on trial-and-error interactions with the environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At a high level, RL is inspired by the way animals and humans learn through positive and negative reinforcement. An RL agent is designed to learn from feedback in the form of rewards or punishments, which are assigned based on its actions in the environment. The agent&amp;rsquo;s goal is to learn a policy, which is a mapping from states to actions that maximizes the expected cumulative reward over time. In other words, the agent attempts to learn a function that allows him to pick the right actions to maximize the reward it receives over the long run.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>RL has been successfully applied to a wide range of problems, including game playing, robotics, and natural language processing. One of the key advantages of RL is its ability to handle complex, uncertain environments in which the optimal policy is not known in advance. RL can also incorporate prior knowledge about the problem domain and can adapt to changes in the environment over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, RL also poses significant challenges, such as the problem of balancing exploration and exploitation, designing effective reward functions, and dealing with high-dimensional state and action spaces. Researchers are actively working on addressing these challenges through the development of new algorithms and techniques.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Overall, RL is a powerful and versatile tool for building intelligent systems that can learn and adapt to new situations through trial and error. As such, it has the potential to revolutionize many fields, from autonomous vehicles to healthcare to finance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Statistics</title><link>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/statistics/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/reinforcement-learning/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://machine-learning-blog.vercel.app/categories/reinforcement-learning/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>